there you go okay
that's where we are
okay Napa means fifth Point fifth of the
Five Points which is we finally reached
okay
all right and uh
the beginning there is very important
because then means uh depending on or
based on what
he says based on that
based on the four steps that came before
that okay so uh based on the four steps
that we've been through
which is what just for someone who's
just tuning in
what was the first step
equal rights second one
yeah it sucks to take care of yourself
all the time
third
it's fun to take care of other people
four
yeah put yourself in other shoes okay
and look back at yourself right
all right good and now we're ready to do
thumbnail okay
okay uh
means how do you meditate on on thumb
then
and that Tibetan word gum their bsgom uh
what's this what's the background
meaning I've done
yeah to get used to something okay so
the Tibetan word for meditation
is to get used to something uh so to you
know
this week you should be doing those uh
exchange of yourself and others on three
levels
every day or or it's not calm get it you
don't get used to it and it doesn't
become part of your behavior you have
the whole point of being in retreat is
to do something over and over again
artificially
so that when you get out of retreat it's
natural okay when you change an attitude
from artificial to Natural that's gum
that's meditation that's the meaning of
meditation the Sanskrit word is even
more sexy
means to be
the word b comes from bhav
so above means to be the ancient
Indo-European is BH EU to become to and
then Anna means
uh maker
so Bob Anna means makes you turn into
that
the word for meditation in Sanskrit
means a practice which makes you turn
into something new
it's very beautiful the the Sanskrit
word for meditation bhavana
means makes you turn into something new
it's very cool the Tibetan
you you develop a habit
there's Sanskrit you become a new person
it's very beautiful okay all right
[Music]
means karuna means compassion okay
compassion
what's the pieces of the Tibetan word
ning is hard jay is like J renpate King
King of Hearts it's a beautiful word
okay
the the Sanskrit karuna
comes into Russian Russian is very
heavily based on Sanskrit
so Krish
Optima Bill Krish
Krishna Dom krisha
the roof and karunamis to cover somebody
or to protect somebody and that's
compassion it's a beautiful uh
word word
means uh
focus on compassion
when you're feeling compassion it means
you want to learn
of Tomlin
what's the land of Tomlin
yeah that means take okay take so you
want to take
the the feeling in your heart when
you're doing the Lemba part when you're
doing the taking part
it should be compassion you know I can't
bear to see you in pain
you know I would like to take it away
from you okay
by the way it is never sacrificial
it is never uh
so get that out of your head you know
it's not me or you it's not somebody has
to suffer it's better if I suffer that's
one of the most irritating unfriendly
practices When someone tells you you
know someone had to eat the bad donut
and I took it
so you didn't have to you know and
you're like Jesus why don't we just
split the good one you know uh
so so you know it's not this kind of
practice where you get to make other
people feel guilty that you took the bad
thing and you know you're supposed to
you're supposed to work it out like a
good negotiation where both parties come
out ahead
there's not this kind of I will
sacrifice what I want and give you what
you want that that kind of thinking is
primitive
that's that's not helpful okay
so uh Timber number and then what will
be the aspect of the or the feeling
in your mind when you do the
yeah it's low it's low in tibetanus
jumper
uh in Sanskrit maitri
my dream comes from all these words uh
which means to mix things
in Russian uh to to mix to mix with
people okay my treat
means it's a difficult word Delta turn
means the flavor of the practice should
be low or the flavor of the practice
should be compassion when you're doing
Tong when you're taking is compassion
when you're giving it's love okay
practice practice
okay get good at it okay John means
practice okay
in any sense Belmar
okay good uh Sawa means the root text
and he keeps quoting books and not
telling you what he's quoting
so luckily you have Grandpa Mike using
Grandpa John's database
I can find stuff you know in a few
seconds
you can search three million pages in
less than three seconds
because of the way we designed it in
1987. whatever okay
[Music]
means those two giving and taking those
two what's
Thelma we lost a beautiful nun here the
most wonderful person Velma
but that's a different Spellman spelling
that spelling is d-p-a-l
which means SRI
which means shining because of burning
and myeloma named her
for a specific reason
pelma
uh bug there's a different pelma s-p-e-l
which means to alternate and those of
you who have done the
the Lion's dance meditation
we practiced uh belma we we practice
jumping between levels okay that's kind
of an advanced meditation practice where
you jump between different levels of
subtlety of the of the mind okay
purposely you come out two levels go
deep three levels come back forth go
that's called Palmer junk okay what's it
mean in Tongan
yeah give take take gift give give give
take take give take it's like uh get
used to switching okay it used to switch
and that's called fluency
in meditation okay and that's a certain
xinjiang right xinjiang
so xinjiang means uh
like fluency in a foreign language where
you speak it with perfect accent
xinjiang means uh
there's a skill in meditation
where you don't just like a dumb
Ox go as deep as you can
there's where you can play between
different levels of focus you can be
creative at one moment
then switch to single single pointed
then switch to a feeling for all living
beings
then switch between them quickly
and that's real Mastery of your mind
okay that's real meditation
it's not the ability only to go deep
it's the ability to go where you want to
go when you want to go and that that
ability leaks out into your everyday
life like if you're a programmer or
something you can
quickly shift focus and
and go deeper when you have a problem
when you hit a problem you can pause and
go much deeper and then extracting the
Mind from the problem
and and quitting the problem and moving
on is is also our meditation skill okay
so basically what he's saying here is
get good at it
your mind should be
what do you call it at your
beck and call yeah your mind does what
you wanted to I like to think of your
mind as a puppy that you bought at the
pet store or even better you pick them
up at the rescue
animal rescue you know and they're kind
of untrained and they pee in the house
and stuff like that and then you train
the dog you know and
and your mind
before you learn to meditate
it's very similar to a bad dog from the
animal rescue you know and then the
whole purpose of meditation
is to train your mind like a it become
like a good dog
and and to obey what you want and to
listen to what you say okay so your your
mind when you start is like a bad thumb
and then you know the purpose of
meditation is to make it more
why
well then you can be more creative in
your work situation problem
and you can think of what other people
need better
and then the company itself starts to be
more successful
if if you
get a Cadre a Cadre means a small secret
group
inside the company
if you have a country of people doing
Tongan that company is probably going to
be successful
okay and they don't have to be Buddhist
you know
Telma in fact was a devout Christian
I went to many Christian classes with
her uh when she started out and it's not
the point to make everybody Buddhist
but the point is to get if you can in
your company or in your non-profit
organization
if if they're all infected with this
virus called tonglin
then the organization becomes wildly
successful
okay it's kind of beautiful it and as
they don't have to
we're gonna get a part here where he
says uh
he says he keeps using the word
anonymous
let your donland be anonymous okay don't
advertise it
you know don't go around saying oh I'm
trying to think of what you want it's
hard you know
you know you're supposed to do it uh
it's a it is a tantric practice
it's a secret practice it's supposed to
be done quietly
okay
the only way you can tell a person doing
tongue land is that they smile a lot
okay they don't talk too much about it
okay somebody
or uh
we are taking the steps we had before
and we are magnifying them
says step five
which is exchanging self in others is an
advanced version of the first four
it's the natural growth of the first
form okay
uh
Denny
he uh in his lecture
he's speaking to a lot of people who
spend a lot of time they didn't have
cell phones so they had to actually
depend on their own mind
and uh
they memorized all these books he just
mentions a line
and everybody knows what book he's
talking about uh we have to look it up
so I looked it up for you
and um
here's the verses he's quoting uh
and I'll I'll go straight there he's
quoting the Lord
which is the seven point lojo lojo means
uh developing bodhichitta okay this low
in low Zhang means body China
Zhang means practice it get good at it
so Lo Zhang means it doesn't mean uh
mental training is an exceptionally poor
translation
it's it's
learning to think like a bodhisattva is
is called lojo okay that's all don't
stop the thinking I don't know
like that uh and the dun dunma is a
famous seven point lojo
tradition says that it existed for many
generations and it was practiced
secretly
and no one wrote it down
and then finally in the uh 12 12th
century
it was written down probably around 11
50. by uh ageshe
named shekawa
and he wrote it down
[Music]
and so here's the verse that Paul Bunyan
which is
mentioning okay and I'll just read it to
you Dila Young
delay
Ed
[Music]
this is the famous lojong text
and it says
if you're practicing
equal rights and what's the second step
Exchange
equal rights and then
put yourself in the other person's shoes
okay when he says you're practicing
those two okay uh and then you want to
do a meditation practice
go down a little more
there you go the big letters okay uh I
always try to make the font size bigger
for the one he's quoting okay uh so the
second line here
means here's a good practice you can do
in samapati
for three dollars
balance meditation
right did you say balance
okay between one and one
between dullness and agitation illness
and agitation okay I'll give you four
bucks
all right uh by the way it's always like
this
you watch a guy crossing the Grand
Canyon on a rope
you know the big toe he's not like just
walking like that he's going
you know or you watch a person's hands
when they drive
they're always moving in fact you can
tell if a driver is new because they
don't move their hands and they tend to
go off the road
so uh you know a person who can talk to
you and drive like this you know then uh
even if it's into a wall
uh
they can that's an inside dining
Mountain joke okay
so like this okay so when they say
summer party it's always like it's like
this you're always what do you call that
correcting as you go okay
then he says
okay try to alternate
between Doha and Limba
sometimes give sometimes take
okay and get good at switching between
the two get good at the switches
and then that's Mastery of your mind
that's xinjiang okay
okay all right
next picture you guys they seem to have
a challenge to get pictures out of these
guys it's a gift
43.9
yeah okay
that's Daniel give me again okay uh
they're gonna talk about
before Nema
what's that mean
giving before taking you have an option
you can take first
give later or you can give first and
take later and it's
huge Topic in the long room
you know there's a huge conversation for
a thousand years and it's beautiful it's
nice to spend the day in those
conversations
you know personally I like to spend a
lot of the day
listening to these conversations okay
it's very
inspiring okay way to spend your day
unless people interrupt okay uh
here we go in the next paragraph okay
foreign
[Music]
there's there's giving and there's
taking okay there's giving and there's
taking okay uh a lot of cheeks a lot of
sources say that you should start with
the giving
okay a lot of sources say that
but in actual practice
I think it's better if you start with
the taking
okay who's he
who's he who's I baboon okay it says you
know I I know people I know there's an
opinion
that maybe you should do the giving
first and then do the taking I prefer uh
doing the taking first and then doing
the giving okay which means which
emotion before which emotion
yeah compassion before love okay
okay
then he says he he says I would go so
far to say
that if you are meditating on any
particular day and you never get to the
tongue it's okay
okay he says I would even go so far to
say that if you if you only do the
taking people's problems
and you never get to giving them
happiness it's okay with me
okay
by the way he's from the greatest
Monastery in the universe
which is Sarah May
there's 12 or 13 colleges out ceremy
he's from the greatest College of the
monastery which is called Guero which is
your college because you're my student
and I'm ghetto so you belong to the very
house
uh of the writer of this long Rim okay
so stick up with your house and never
think about the other houses okay
all right
uh he says look and there's the famous
example of a kid who falls off their
bicycle okay you don't give them candy
first and then put a Band-Aid on their
knee
okay first you fix the problem
and then you give them candy because
when you give a candy to a kid whose
knee is bleeding it's not taste it
doesn't taste that good to the kid okay
so generally it's a lime Rim principle
that you have to take care of
other people's hurt
before you give them happiness okay that
makes large it's logical right they
can't enjoy their happiness
if they're still hurting better to take
away the hurt first and then give them
happiness
I think a lot of men
tend to give
there was to try to give them happiness
without trying to understand them or
take away their pain first they just
like oh look I got you a mean coat you
know and she's like yeah I was hoping
you'd just come home once in a while you
know and something like that okay
okay anyway
uh
then he gets into
razors okay you guys you got a picture
here for me
yeah and and he's gonna make a
he wants you when you do the taking
he wants you to do a hard operation he
wants you to go into the other person's
chest
and go find the Blackness and in public
repachay's version
you cut it with a razor
okay you cut you cut the you imagine a
straight razor
and you cut the you cut the Blackness
out and you take it okay so it has to be
a surgical
strike
you don't want to take out the heart
you're just taking out like so it's a
very precision
Precision thing
go in and
slice
off the Blackness and imagine that you
are slicing it off okay
you're a man
uh a male
uh
that's me getting a haircut
like a couple days ago and this is my
favorite Barber his name is Mr Robbie
and uh he gives haircuts out on the
street in San Diego and uh
so it's outside he was a gang member in
LA or something
and he learned to cut hair and he's
really good at it
uh even someone who doesn't have hair
will look like they have hair and uh
and uh me and Veronica love to go there
and we love to hang out with him and
place
really good r b mixes uh loud on the
sidewalk and and you're in the sun line
and it's really fun but anyway
and I have
he by the way he's the best uh Miss MBA
she goes
he's the best entrepreneur I ever met
I can say that
he was living in his car
and now he owns like three beauty salons
four Mustangs
has a beautiful family
um
so anyway
exactly one of the most successful
entrepreneurs I know
and uh so anyway one day my wife said
give Michael a shave with one of those
straight razors you know and I'm like no
that's okay
[Music]
and uh he's like wow there's enough and
when they get near the jugular
which is here
um I get really nervous like I don't
know
Mr Robbie says every man should have a
straight razor shave once in his life
and I've done it once and did you ever
do it randomly no it just feels too
dangerous to me uh
so I sat through the whole thing it
takes about 45 minutes or something and
uh anyway
when I think of this Tomlin and I think
of the the lamba the taking
I always think of Mr Robbie and uh so
it's a surgical
thing you know you go to your heart you
go to the other person's heart you go
inside their body you go to their heart
and you take the razor of your
meditation and you slice off the
darkness okay got it that's the that's
the long Runway okay
all right
um
means a razor blade
a straight razor and by the way they use
them every day in the monastery
because that's how you shave someone's
head and it's a favorite thing
for months to go out and sit in the Sun
and your best friend shaves your head
and they shout they lather it up and
they get they shame and you talk about
stuff you talk about how mean is your
scripture teacher and stuff like that
and it's a pleasant way to spend the
like I have power with your friend okay
um
means to shave
darling
[Music]
Timber some okay uh take the
slice off their problems uh as a black
light it's kind of a
contradiction of terms it's a black
light one knocker number in in the form
take it to your heart and feed it to
your Ron shenzen
feed it to your selfishness you know you
wanna get something from other people
here take this
this is their suffering okay you're
always trying to get something out of
other people right yeah you want to take
care of yourself right yeah you want to
take take take right yeah okay take
their suffering okay here you go
okay and it's very cool the Tibetan is
you know feeded to your selfishness you
want something from other people here
take this you know it's very beautiful
the language is very beautiful
okay now he's gonna describe
uh and I'd like you to practice this
meditation today okay so this is your
homework assignment
up in the valley we have a special
Valley here
which is dedicated to retreat
and by the way we have a deal with the
fort which is a deal with the federal
government and the County government we
cannot build more cabinets there
and uh legally and so it will always be
a retreat Valley
and and they'll always be quiet
those beautiful comments there they are
really beautiful
so
you're gonna practice it today okay
our Critter we got
hmm
I don't know what that is
okay
what's that Jiggy
oh it's a quail okay
all right next picture you guys
this is a book it was one of the first
books I ever worked on it was about the
Wheel of Life
it's about a Sutra
uh that tells the story of when the
Buddha first painted The Wheel of Life
and I translated it with my teacher
I don't know
45 years ago
okay and uh if you knew Robert Lacy I
don't think you guys knew him
he he input the first book for for all
he typed the first book
it was the Kellogg to become your
he typed it in the in a tiny apartment
in the Westville in the West Village
very dangerous apartment
uh and uh
so he did the drawing and um
this is a
this was uh also the first time that uh
Tibetan was ever done on a computer
printed on a computer was this book
uh so and it was printed on a
dot matrix a laser printer at bell bell
Laboratories in New Jersey a million
dollar laser printer We snuck in at
night and used it uh so anyway uh
we're gonna work through the Realms okay
in the middle of the Demon's hands
are the five Realms of existence okay uh
sometimes uh drawn as six all right uh
traditionally the ancient instruction is
changmapa which means make it in five
parts
Pancha gatta and um
and sugan has translated an unbelievable
uh text about this wheel
and that's coming out very soon
and uh we're just doing the last parts
of it but
this is a good way to visualize the
Realms okay and we'll we'll talk more
about it tomorrow or sorry in the next
class
uh
but these are the Realms of existence
inside the wheel okay
so we're going to be working through the
realms
and um
there's a wonderful treatment in Sue
gang's book so again finish this book
two years ago we've been cleaning it for
two years
and he went on to a
a very difficult commentary by Vasa
Bandu which which no one has ever
translated
in uh
if you know Vasa Bandu
he wrote uh
avidame which is the
Mother book of all abhidharma school
this is the first of the four schools
okay
the lowest of the four Buddhist schools
and Stanley's got a 26 year project
he's six years through that's why we
chose a young one
he was young at the time
so we'll work into that book but Vasa
Bandu was actually a closet mind only
School
he was actually the greatest one of the
greatest thinkers of the Mind only
school so he wrote
an explanation
of The Wheel of Life from the mind only
School
and he's the only person who ever did
that and uh
he found it John Brady's project founded
and it's long and it's extremely
difficult so that's what sugang is
chewing on now like a piece of hard
leather
okay uh
so we'll be going into that meditation
how to do The Taking of the suffering
and rather than doing it here at Diamond
Mountain
or in this Retreat online rather than
doing it with one other person
we're gonna start out with the five
Realms okay okay we're gonna do it
for each realm and that takes some
explanation okay and that's why you have
to tune in for the next show in half an
hour so please take a nice break
and we'll see you guys in half an hour